I'd like to begin by asking you why you
think that we should
care about animals and why our dietary choices are so important.
Why we should care about animals is because we effect them and it's important to know how we effect
them and to be able to really take
responsibility for that.
The key for me is the relationship
between sentience and sovereignty.
Sentience is the capacity for something
to feel,
to suffer, to love, to want
and sovereignty is its freedom to direct
its own life.
And I think the essential insight
on the topic of rights, whether we're
talking about
rights of other races, rights of
women, rights of any group that has been
marginalized, rights other species,
is that if something
is sentient, it should be acknowledged
as sovereign.
If something has the ability to suffer or
to experience joy, if it can feel,
it should get to direct its own life
according to what would optimize those
feelings for it.
Earlier in human history,
we've subjugated other people in ways
that we no longer find okay, through slavery,
through patriarchal domination and when we progressively came to recognize,
women or people with another skin color or
kids, they feel as much as we do and their
life matters and they should have the
same sovereign rights,
it's really the next extension of that
now to
all the other animal species. And empathy
is really this progressive process of
recognizing that things that are
different than us
have similarities with us. At first if
someone had a different skin color from us,
we could make them different enough
then we could torture them and think it
was okay and
with more awareness and empathy we start to recognize there's actually more similarity,
there was enough similarity between us.
that we can relate to their experience
and then it wasn't okay to inflict an
experience and then we wouldn't want.
And the truth is even though animals are
very different than us
and many ways, they share hurt
and suffering and love and
playfulness and depending upon where in
the evolutionary spectrum they are they,
show those things more less
but the ability to feel pain is all the
way down the most fundamental animals.
Recognizing that, we need to take
responsibility for how effect them.